I bring Sutekh's gift of death.
‫"في الحلقة السابقة"
For you.
‫من أجلك.
And for all of this tiny,
‫ولكل كونك
vile, incessant universe.
‫الضئيل والمنحط والمزعج.
Doctor!
‫دكتور!
All of you, everyone, get out!
‫اخرجوا جميعًا!
- All of you, get out! Get out! Go! - I bring Sutekh's dust of death.
‫- اخرجوا جميعًا! ‫- أجلب غبار الموت من "سوتيخ".
Come on! Let's go!
‫هيا! لنذهب!
Doc! Come on! Let's go!
‫هيا يا دكتور! لنذهب!
Hop on, cowboy.
‫اركب يا راعي البقر.
We're on our way back. Try to contain that thing.
‫نحن في طريق العودة. ‫حاولي احتواء ذلك الشيء.
- I bring Sutekh's dust of death. - Open fire. All weapons.
‫- أجلب غبار الموت من "سوتيخ". ‫- أطلقوا النار بكل الأسلحة.
Why can't I see her?
‫لماذا لا يمكنني رؤيتها؟
All the bullets turned to dust, ma'am.
‫تحولت الطلقات إلى غبار يا سيدتي.
Oh, one day.
‫يا للهول.
I bring Sutekh's dust of death.
‫أجلب غبار الموت من "سوتيخ".
Doctor, are you there?
‫هل تسمعني يا دكتور؟
This is me signing off with thanks and love.
‫هذه أنا أنهي خدمتي بكل شكر وحُب.
And please send this monster back into hell.
‫وأرجوك أن تعد هذا الوحش إلى الجحيم.
No!
‫لا!
Because I have to hope the birds will sing again.
‫لأن عليّ التحلي بالأمل ‫أن الطيور ستغرّد مجددًا.
There will be birds.
‫ستكون هناك طيور.
There's nothing we can do...
‫لا يُوجد ما يسعنا فعله…
- except fight.
‫باستثناء القتال.
Faster! Mel, faster!
‫أسرعي يا "ميل"!
I'm going as fast as I can!
‫أنطلق بأقصى سرعة ممكنة!
No, I mean faster!
‫لا، أعني أسرع!
We're gonna die!
‫سنموت!
Mel, go right!
‫انعطفي يمينًا يا "ميل".
We interrupt this broadcast
‫نقطع هذا البث
with warnings of an incident in central London.
‫بتحذيرات عن وقوع حادث في وسط "لندن".
People are being told to evacuate the city immediately.
‫يُطلب من الناس إخلاء المدينة على الفور.
What is it? What's going on?
‫ما الأمر؟ ماذا يحدث؟
Do you believe in the power of prayer?
‫هل تؤمنين بقوة الدعاء؟
I most certainly do.
‫بكل تأكيد.
Then tell your Maker
‫أخبري خالقك إذًا
I will come to storm down his gates of gold
‫بأنني سآتي لأقتحم بواباته الذهبية
and seize his kingdom in my true name.
‫وأستولي على مملكته باسمي الحقيقي.
Who-- Who are you?
‫من أنت؟
I'm sorry, you tiny, little woman.
‫آسفة أيتها المرأة الضئيلة.
I'm so, so sorry it ends like this.
‫أنا آسفة لأن الأمر سينتهي هكذا.
I had such plans.
‫كانت لديّ خطط للمستقبل.
Time Membrane failing.
‫قصور في الغشاء الزمني.
You, get out. Bunker 17 now.
‫اخرجي واذهبي إلى الغرفة المحصنة 17.
- Doctor, my mother. Why can't we see her? - Ruby, we have got worse problems.
‫- دكتور، لم لا يمكننا رؤية أمي؟ ‫- "روبي"، لدينا مشكلات أسوأ.
Okay.
‫حسنًا.
It's a TARDIS remembered.
‫إنها ذكرى لـ"تارديس".
It's made of memories.
‫إنها مصنوعة من الذكريات.
Ruby, it is feeding off you.
‫"روبي"، إنها تستمد قوّتها منك.
Yeah, give it everything you've got, babes. Remember it harder.
‫ابذلي قصارى جهدك. تذكّري بشكل أقوى.
Yes, yes. Yes, I can. Yes.
‫حسنًا. أستطيع ذلك.
If time is a memory, then memory is a time machine.
‫إن كان الزمن الذكرى، فالذكرى آلة زمن.
Yes. Yes. That's it.
‫أجل. أحسنت.
More. More, more, more.
‫أقوى.
That should do it.
‫سيكفي هذا.
Okay.
‫حسنًا.
Doctor!
‫دكتور!
We meet again, my old friend.
‫نلتقي مجددًا يا صديقي القديم.
Don't you dare.
‫إياك!
Doctor, what is that thing?
‫دكتور، ما ذلك الشيء؟
Sutekh. The Death of Ages.
‫"سوتيخ". "موت الدهور".
The Typhonian Beast.
‫"الوحش التايفوني".
The greatest monster I have ever fought.
‫أعظم وحش واجهته على الإطلاق.
If Sutekh is so totally evil,
‫إن كان "سوتيخ" شريرًا جدًا،
why didn't Horus and the other Osirans destroy him?
‫فلماذا لم يدمره ‫"حورس" والأوزيريون الآخرون؟
- The Time Window has my memories too. - It was against their code.
‫- النافذة الزمنية بها ذكرياتي أيضًا. ‫- خالف ذلك معتقدهم.
To have killed him would've meant that they were no better than he...
‫قتلهم له يعني أنهم ليسوا أفضل منه…
It's your life, Doctor. - ...so they simply imprisoned him.
‫- إنها حياتك يا دكتور. ‫- …لذا سجنوه فحسب.
It's telling the story of your life.
‫إنها تسرد قصة حياتك.
A long time ago, in the England of 1911,
‫قبل وقت طويل، في "إنكلترا" سنة 1911،
Sutekh had been bound and imprisoned for all eternity.
‫رُبط وسُجن "سوتيخ" إلى الأبد.
But he rose again, and I defeated him.
‫لكنه قام مجددًا وهزمته.
I cast you into the Time Vortex.
‫ألقيت بك في "دوامة الزمن".
I sent you forward to your own death.
‫أرسلتك إلى المستقبل لتلاقي حتفك.
Instead, I found a home.
‫وجدت بيتًا لي بدلًا من ذلك.
I clung to your infernal machine,
‫تشبثت بآلتك الجحيمية،
and for so many years, I hid.
‫واختبأت لسنوات كثيرة.
I have travelled with you for all this time,
‫سافرت معك طوال هذا الوقت،
riding the spine of your ship,
‫ممتطيًا هيكل سفينتك،
staring into eternity and evolving into my true godhood.
‫محدّقًا إلى الأبدية ‫ومتطورًا إلى ذاتي الإلهية الحقيقية.
Now I know every beat of the heart of your time machine,
‫الآن أعرف كلّ دقائق وتفاصيل آلتك الزمنية،
and I can bend it to my will.
‫وبوسعي إخضاعها لإرادتي.
It will stand as my altar.
‫سأجعلها مذبحًا لي.
The temple of my empire of death.
‫معبد إمبراطوريتي للموت.
But I saw inside the TARDIS.
‫لكنني رأيت "تارديس" من الداخل.
So many secrets.
‫ثمة أسرار كثيرة.
Her name.
‫اسمها.
- Susan. The perfect trap.
‫- "سوزان". ‫- الفخ المثالي.
I created an apparition of her universe
‫صنعت تجسيدًا لعالمها…
so that every time we landed on every single world,
‫…لذا كلما هبطنا في كلّ عالم،
I birthed them all.
‫أنجبتهنّ جميعًا.
My angels of death,
‫ملائكة الموت،
now standing triumphant across the universe.
‫الآن هن منتصرات عبر الكون.
I bring Sutekh's dust of death.
‫أجلب غبار الموت من "سوتيخ".
Every living thing is an abomination.
‫كلّ كائن حي بغيض.
I am come to release them into blessed deaths.
‫جئت لأحررهم إلى الموت المبارك.
And I find that good.
‫وأرى أن ذلك حسن.
And I damn you, Sutekh.
‫وأنا ألعنك يا "سوتيخ".
I damn you in the name of life itself.
‫ألعنك باسم الحياة ذاتها.
And I swear to you,
‫وأقسم لك،
with both the hearts of the last of the Time Lords,
‫بكلا قلبي آخر أسياد الزمن،
I will stop you.
‫إنني سأوقفك.
I will defeat you.
‫وسأهزمك.
And I will turn back death.
‫وسأعكس الموت.
And why am I still alive?
‫ولماذا ما زلت أنا حيًا؟
Killing me is your gift.
‫قتلي هو هبتك.
And believe me, Sutekh, I am an extinction event.
‫وصدّقني يا "سوتيخ"، ‫قتلي يعني انقراضًا جماعيًا لقومي.
So, what is stopping you?
‫ما الذي يمنعك إذًا؟
Why is the god of death not killing me?
‫لماذا لا يقتلني إله الموت؟
What am I missing?
‫ما الذي يفوتني؟
I'll tell you a secret, Sute.
‫سأخبرك بسر يا "سوت".
This feeling that you have now, this doubt...
‫هذا الشعور الذي يراودك الآن، هذا الشك…
Have you ever felt so alive?
‫هل شعرت بهذا القدر من الإثارة قط؟
And doesn't it feel good?
‫أوليس شعورًا جيدًا؟
Run.
‫اهربا.
- What is it? It's a remembered TARDIS.
‫- ما هذه؟ ‫- هذه ذكرى لـ"تارديس".
It's bits and pieces of every TARDIS that ever was.
‫أجزاء متفرقة من كلّ "تارديس" ‫في أشكالها المختلفة.
Held together by hopes and wishes and luck.
‫متماسكة معًا بالآمال والأماني والحظ.
Wait. Does this thing work? Can it fly?
‫مهلًا. هل تعمل؟ أيمكنها الطيران؟
No idea.
‫لا أعرف.
No! No, no, no, no, no, no, no! We need that!
‫لا! نحتاج إلى ذلك!
Tie that to that.
‫أعقدي هذه بتلك.
- Yeah? We're good. - All right.
‫- جيد. ‫- حسنًا.
- Oh. - Mel?
‫"ميل"؟
- What? - Tie that lever down.
‫- ماذا؟ ‫- اربطي تلك الذراع.
All those switches, down, down, down. Yeah?
‫وكلّ تلك المفاتيح.
Ruby, see these wires?
‫"روبي"، أترين هذه الأسلاك؟
Tie them together. Tie them tight.
‫اعقديها معًا بإحكام.
Doctor, we're on fire.
‫دكتور، "تارديس" مشتعلة.
- Is this thing safe? - Absolute death trap, Melanie B.
‫- أهي آمنة؟ ‫- إنها شرك موت يا "ميلاني بي".
Okay.
‫حسنًا.
Yeah, that's better.
‫أجل، هذا أفضل.
- Okay. Okay, that's it.
‫حسنًا. هكذا.
That's it.
‫هكذا.
Calm down.
‫اهدئي.
Oh, no, no.
‫لا.
That's it. Nice and easy.
‫هكذا. برفق وروية.
Okay.
‫حسنًا.
That hook is a molecular bond.
‫هذا الحبل رابط جزيئي.
- It's like intelligent rope. - What? You mean, like--
‫- إنه مثل حبل ذكي. ‫- ماذا؟ أتعني مثل…
Intelligent glove.
‫القفاز الذكي.
That was the first day we met.
‫كان ذلك في أول يوم التقينا.
Man, I am so sorry.
‫أنا آسف جدًا.
We've gotta stabilise.
‫يجب أن نوازنها.
Because without the Time Window's memories, we go kaboom.
‫لأننا سننفجر ‫من دون ذكريات النافذة الزمنية.
That screen is holding the TARDIS together.
‫هذه الشاشة هي ما يتسبب في تماسك "تارديس".
Okay.
‫حسنًا.
So, what did I miss?
‫ما الذي فاتني؟
Every Susan Triad, they were innocent?
‫هل كلّ "سوزان ترياد" كنّ بريئات؟
- They were all real? - Absolutely real.
‫- كلهنّ حقيقيات؟ ‫- حقيقيات بالتأكيد.
Every time the TARDIS would land, it would roll her out like...
‫في كلّ مرة تهبط "تارديس"، تظهر نسخة منها…
Okay, so the-- the TARDIS has a perception filter
‫في "تارديس" مرشّح إدراكي
so it doesn't get noticed. It just sits there, kind of unseen.
‫كيلا تُلاحظ. إنها تقبع في مكانها ولا تُرى.
'Cause it casts a field around it at 66.7 metres exactly.
‫لأنها تطلق حقلًا حولها ‫بنصف قطر 66.7 مترًا بالضبط.
Seventy-three yards.
‫73 ياردة.
How do you know that?
‫كيف عرفت ذلك؟
I don't-- I don't know. I just do.
‫لا أدري. أعرفه فحسب.
Funny things happen at 73 yards.
‫أشياء غريبة تحدث على بُعد 66.7 مترًا.
People say that you can see things.
‫يقول الناس إن بوسعهم رؤية أشياء.
So, Sutekh, he used this field, but he used it massively.
‫استخدم "سوتيخ" هذا الحقل، لكن بشكل هائل.
He focused his mind
‫ركّز ذهنه
and created a whole new person everywhere I'd land.
‫وصنع شخصًا جديدًا أينما هبطت.
But perception means that she fitted in. She had character.
‫لكن الإدراك يعني أنها تلاءمت. ‫كانت لديها شخصية.
She had history. She had a truth.
‫كان لديها تاريخ وحقيقة.
But Doctor, you landed on Earth a hundred times.
‫لكنك هبطت على "الأرض" ‫مئات المرات يا دكتور.
I think that she was reborn every time.
‫أظن أنها وُلدت من جديد في كلّ مرة.
Each time the TARDIS would land, the idea of that woman would get stronger.
‫في كلّ مرة تهبط "تارديس" فيها، ‫تزداد قوة فكرة وجود تلك المرأة.
By 2024, she was Susan Triad.
‫وبحلول 2024، صارت "سوزان ترياد".
This monumental figure.
‫تلك الشخصية البارزة.
What has she done? Sutekh called her an angel of death.
‫ماذا فعلت؟ دعاها "سوتيخ" بملاك الموت.
What did she do?
‫ماذا فعلت؟
The dust of death.
‫غبار الموت.
Spreading all over the world.
‫ينتشر حول العالم.
- My mother, is she-- It's everyone.
‫- هل أمي… ‫- الجميع.
- No, but can't you just-- - Nothing I can do.
‫- لكن ألا يمكنك… ‫- لا يمكنني فعل شيء.
It's happening over and over again.
‫يحدث الأمر مرارًا وتكرارًا.
Every time I landed there.
‫في كلّ مرة هبطت هناك.
1999...
‫في سنة 1999…
1066...
‫وفي سنة 1066…
2005.
‫وفي سنة 2005.
The Earth is dying.
‫"الأرض" تُحتضر.
So many times.
‫مرارًا وتكرارًا.
Every world that I ever stood upon...
‫كلّ عالم هبطت عليه…
All dead.
‫كلّها ماتت.
Venus.
‫"الزهرة".
Telos. Karn.
‫"تيلوس". "كارن".
The Ood-Sphere.
‫"أود سفير".
- And Skaro. - The Daleks are dead.
‫- و"سكارو". ‫- مات الـ"داليك".
Everything is dead.
‫مات كلّ شيء.
But--
‫لكن…
There are so many places you haven't been.
‫ثمة أماكن كثيرة لم تزرها.
They must be safe.
‫لا بد أنها آمنة.
I've travelled so far.
‫سافرت كثيرًا.
Everything caught in that pattern is dying.
‫كلّ شيء علق في ذلك النمط يُحتضر.
The whole of time and space.
‫الزمان والمكان بأكملهما.
I did this.
‫فعلت هذا.
You did not.
‫لم تفعله.
No.
‫لا.
Every sun is dead.
‫ماتت كلّ شمس.
The universe has come to a halt.
‫توقّف الكون تمامًا.
And it is my fault.
‫وهي غلطتي.
'Cause I travelled to all those worlds.
‫لأنني زرت كلّ تلك العوالم.
I thought it was fun.
‫حسبت زيارتها ممتعة.
The universe stands silent in death.
‫الكون صامت في الموت.
Yet one thing persists.
‫مع ذلك، ثمة شيء يثابر.
One thing keeps living despite me.
‫يواصل شيء الحياة رغمًا عني.
The Time Lord.
‫سيد الزمن.
No. Greater than him.
‫لا. شيء أعظم منه.
A secret the child carries with her.
‫سرّ تحمله الفتاة داخلها.
But I will find them.
‫لكنني سأعثر عليهم.
Out there...
‫هناك في تجاويف هذا الكون المقفر،
they are hiding somewhere, lost in the wind and the wilds.
‫يختبئون في مكان ما، ‫تائهان في الرياح والقفار.
Excuse me.
‫المعذرة.
Can you tell me...
‫أيمكنك إخباري
...where are we?
‫أين نحن؟
No idea.
‫لا أعرف.
Absolutely no idea, darling.
‫لا أعرف مطلقًا يا عزيزي.
All I've got is this chaffee. Do you want some?
‫ليس لديّ إلا مشروب تشافي. أتريد كوبًا؟
That's very kind. J-- Only if you have enough.
‫هذا لطف منك. إن كان لديك ما يكفي فحسب.
Where did you come from?
‫من أين أتيت؟
Nowhere. [sighs] Um, I-- I got a bit lost.
‫من لا مكان. ضللت طريقي.
I haven't seen anyone in weeks.
‫لم أر أحدًا طوال أسابيع.
There was a caravan that passed through, heading towards--
‫مرّت قافلة من هنا ومتجهة إلى…
I don't know, somewhere over that way.
‫لا أعرف، إلى مكان ما في ذلك الاتجاه.
They said there was food, but I haven't seen them since.
‫قالوا إنه يُوجد طعام هناك، ‫لكنني لم أرهم ثانيةً.
Hush now, darling. Let me give the man his chaffee.
‫صهي يا عزيزتي. سأعطي الرجل مشروب التشافي.
Who is the little one?
‫من الصغيرة؟
I think I called her Brindle.
‫أظن أنني دعوتها "بريندل".
Brindle Dee.
‫"بريندل دي".
But I forget.
‫لكنني نسيت.
What is this place called?
‫ماذا يُدعى هذا المكان؟
Hard to remember. I--
‫يصعب تذكّر اسمه.
They say memory is dying.
‫يقولون إن الذكرى تُحتضر.
There was a man that said that actual facts were dying in the death wave.
‫قال رجل إن الحقائق كانت تُحتضر ‫في موجة الموت.
But I think this was the city of...
‫لكنني أظن أنها كانت مدينة…
It began with a B.
‫يبدأ اسمها بحرف "ب".
And the planet?
‫والكوكب؟
I don't think I was born here.
‫لا أظن أنني وُلدت هنا.
Then I met my husband.
‫ثم قابلت زوجي.
Whatever his name was.
‫أيًا كان اسمه.
Tall. He was tall.
‫كان طويلًا.
I remember that.
‫أتذكّر ذلك.
But it was all a very long time ago.
‫لكن كان هذا قبل وقت طويل جدًا.
Well, at least you survived.
‫على الأقل أنت نجوت.
I'm not sure I did, really.
‫لست متأكدة من أنني نجوت حقًا.
The funny thing is,
‫الأمر الغريب،
I do remember an opera house over that way.
‫هو أنني أتذكّر دار أوبرا من ذلك الاتجاه.
Of all the things to remember.
‫من بين الأشياء التي يمكن تذكّرها.
Maybe I worked there. Maybe I sang.
‫ربما عملت هناك وربما غنّيت.
But people used to come from all over.
‫لكن كان يحضر الناس من كلّ مكان.
The lights and the diamonds and all sorts of things. It was lovely.
‫الأضواء والماسات وأشياء كثيرة مختلفة. ‫كانت جميلة.
Have you got any metal?
‫هل لديك أي معدن؟
Metal is a precious thing, sir.
‫المعدن شيء ثمين يا سيدي.
I don't think anything is precious anymore.
‫لا أظن أنه ما زال هناك شيء ثمين.
I suppose you do have a very nice face.
‫أظن أن ملامحك تعكس أنك شخص لطيف.
- I'll forget it in a minute. - That's very kind of you.
‫- سأنساها بعد قليل. ‫- هذا لطف شديد منك.
I will use this spoon. I promise.
‫أعدك بأنني سأستخدم هذه الملعقة.
Might save the universe with this spoon.
‫ربما سأنقذ الكون بهذه الملعقة.
That would be nice.
‫سيكون ذلك لطيفًا.
You should go now.
‫عليك الرحيل الآن.
Are you-- you okay?
‫هل أنت بخير؟
I think my daughter died, didn't she?
‫أظن أن ابنتي ماتت، أليس كذلك؟
And I forgot.
‫وأنا نسيت.
I think she did.
‫أظن أنها ماتت.
I'm sorry.
‫أنا آسف.
They say it travels, the death wave, down the family line.
‫يقولون إن موجة الموت تنتقل من جيل إلى جيل.
Except that this man, he said it's--
‫باستثناء ذلك الرجل، قال…
it's-- it's perverse. That's what he said.
‫قال إنها فاسدة.
That it's so determined to kill that it can travel backwards.
‫وإنها عازمة على القتل ‫لدرجة أن بوسعها الانتقال إلى الجيل السابق.
From child to mother.
‫من الطفل إلى الأم.
But it's okay because I really am very tired.
‫لكن لا بأس، لأنني منهكة جدًا.
You've got such a nice face.
‫وجهك لطيف جدًا.
I swear to you with a spoon.
‫أقسم لك بتلك الملعقة.
That's what we need.
‫هذا ما نحتاج إليه.
Just some metal, not a TARDIS memory. Something real.
‫قطعة معدن، وليس ذكرى لـ"تارديس". ‫بل شيء حقيقي.
Thank you, whoever you were.
‫أشكرك أيًا كنت.
Look, look, look.
‫انظري.
After all this time, it's still connected to the Time Window.
‫بعد مرور كلّ هذا الوقت، ‫ما زالت مرتبطة بالنافذة الزمنية.
Yeah, I never understood what was all that Egyptian stuff?
‫أجل، لم أفهم قط ‫ما كانت كلّ تلك الأشياء المصرية؟
Cultural appropriation.
‫سرقة ثقافية.
Release me!
‫أطلقني!
They just travelled in the TARDIS.
‫سافرا في "تارديس" فحسب.
...or I shall destroy the cosmos! - That's how I know Mel.
‫- …وإلا فسأدمر الكون! ‫- هكذا تعرّفت إلى "ميل".
- We travelled together, didn't we? - Hmm.
‫سافرنا معًا، أليس كذلك؟
Best time of my life.
‫أفضل فترة في حياتي.
We met Einstein.
‫قابلنا "أينشتاين".
I'll spare the planet Earth. Did we?
‫- سأعفو عن كوكب "الأرض". ‫- حقًا؟
I'll give it to you as a plaything.
‫سأعطيه لك لتلعب به.
- God, I'd forgotten. Release me!
‫- رباه، لقد نسيت. ‫- أطلقني!
- You okay? No, Sutekh...
‫- هل أنت بخير؟ ‫- لا يا "سوتيخ"…
Exhausted.
‫أنا منهكة.
I don't get it. What changed? No!
‫- ما زلت لم أفهم. ما الذي تغيّر؟ ‫- لا!
Sutekh was hidden for years. Why did he go on the attack?
‫كان "سوتيخ" مختفيًا لسنوات. ‫لماذا قرر الهجوم؟
- Ask that again.
‫- كرري سؤالك. ‫- لماذا قرر الهجوم؟
Why did Sutekh appear on Ruby Road?
‫لماذا ظهر "سوتيخ" في شارع "روبي"؟
It's answering you.
‫إنها تجيبك.
The images are reaching out to you.
‫تتواصل الصور معك.
- What do you mean? They're trying to help.
‫- ماذا تقصد؟ ‫- إنها تحاول المساعدة.
The Time Window is still connected to your memories.
‫ما زالت النافذة الزمنية مرتبطة بذكرياتك.
Maybe it's trying to ask you something.
‫ربما تحاول طرح سؤال عليك.
But what does this have to do with my mother?
‫لكن ما علاقة هذا بأمي؟
Oh, because-- because...
‫لأن…
Sutekh became visible outside the church,
‫صار "سوتيخ" مرئيًا خارج الكنيسة،
because when he landed with the TARDIS in 2004,
‫لأنه عندما هبط مع "تارديس" في 2004،
he saw the one thing beyond his comprehension.
‫رأى الشيء الوحيد الذي لم يتمكن من فهمه.
- Your mother. - But who is she?
‫- أمك. ‫- لكن من تكون؟
We don't know. And neither does he. That's the point.
‫لا نعرف ولا هو يعرف. ذلك بيت القصيد.
Look.
‫انظري.
She drives us crazy, but Sutekh, oh.
‫إنها تثير جنوننا، لكن "سوتيخ"؟
He's been riding on the back of the TARDIS beholding all of time and space,
‫كان يمتطي "تارديس" ‫ويرى الزمن والمكان بأكملهما،
and then he can't see one woman. One woman.
‫ثم فجأة لم يتمكن من رؤية امرأة واحدة.
One singular, mysterious woman.
‫امرأة غامضة ومنفردة.
No wonder he's keeping us alive. To figure out the answer. Who is she?
‫لا عجب أنه يبقينا أحياء ‫ليعثر على الإجابة. من هي؟
But if gods are scared of her, then what the hell does that mean?
‫لكن إن كانت الآلهة تخشاها، فما معنى ذلك؟
She's not this big cosmic thing, is she? Because in that case, what am I?
‫ليست كائنًا كونيًا مهمًا، ‫لأنها إن كانت كذلك، فماذا أكون؟
Ruby, you are absolutely human.
‫"روبي"، أنت بشرية تمامًا.
But who is she?
‫لكن من هي؟
- And why was she pointing at you? - Hey. Hey, hey.
‫- ولماذا كانت تشير إليك؟ ‫- اهدئي.
Hey. Come here.
‫اقتربي.
Melanie.
‫"ميلاني".
I see you.
‫أراك.
We can find the living...
‫بوسعنا أن نعثر على الأحياء
- ...through time and space
‫عبر الزمان والمكان
and family.
‫والعائلة.
I wish there was something we could do to just see her.
‫ليت هناك ما يسعنا فعله لرؤيتها.
But the government says--
‫لكن الحكومة تقول…
- What government? - Okay, then who's that?
‫- أي حكومة؟ ‫- حسنًا، من ذاك؟
I mean, the government has collapsed in shame.
‫"انتخابات 2046"
- In absolute shame, Amol. - Let me see.
‫- في خزي تام يا "أمول". ‫- أريني.
Now's the time to vote.
‫حان الآن وقت التصويت.
No, nothing.
‫لا أرى شيئًا.
Give it to me.
‫أعطها لي.
There. I mean him.
‫هناك. أعنيه.
- In particular, the DNA testing regime. - It's giving you another answer.
‫- خاصةً نظام اختبار الحمض النووي. ‫- إنها تعطيك إجابة أخرى.
- That's the guy off the TV, but who's he? - I'm trying to make life better.
‫- إنه شخص على التلفاز، لكن من هو؟ ‫- أحاول تحسين المعيشة.
I propose compulsory DNA testing for the entire population.
‫أقترح اختبار حمض نووي إلزاميًا للشعب كله.
The most dangerous prime minister in history.
‫أخطر رئيس وزراء في التاريخ.
But that's 2046.
‫لكن هذا في 2046.
You haven't met him, have you?
‫لم تلتقي به، أليس كذلك؟
No. No, I couldn't. Could I?
‫لا يمكنني هذا. أليس كذلك؟
Then why is it showing you?
‫لماذا تريك هذا إذًا؟
2046. 2046.
‫2046.
2046! He did it!
‫2046! فعلها!
DNA testing became compulsory for the entire population in the UK.
‫صار اختبار الحمض النووي إلزاميًا ‫لكل سكان "المملكة المتحدة".
- So if your mother was still alive... - She'd be on record.
‫- لذا إن كانت والدتك ما زالت حية… ‫- فستكون مدرجة.
She would be on the register.
‫سيكون حمضها النووي في النظام.
We've never been able to find her because she never got tested.
‫لم نتمكن من العثور عليها ‫لأنها لم تُختبر قط.
But 2046, she's got no choice.
‫لكن في 2046، ليس لديها خيار.
It is showing us the way, Ruby. It's showing us the path to your mother.
‫ترينا الطريق يا "روبي". ‫ترينا كيف نعثر على أمك.
- If I can just-- - What does that mean?
‫- إن استطعت… ‫- ماذا يعني ذلك؟
- Can we find Ruby's mother? - Yeah. And what happens if we do?
‫- أيمكننا أن نجد والدة "روبي"؟ ‫- أجل. وماذا سيحدث حينها؟
One question at a time.
‫سؤال واحد في المرة.
Okay.
‫حسنًا.
All right. The TARDIS doesn't have much power...
‫لا تملك "تارديس" الكثير من الطاقة،
...but if it can just make one final--
‫لكن إن استطعنا إجراء قفزة…
Handy. Love a whistle.
‫إنها مفيدة. أُحب الصفارات.
- 2046, here we come! - But 2046 doesn't exist, does it?
‫- 2046، ها نحن قادمون! ‫- لكن لا وجود لـ2046، أليس كذلك؟
Yes, but it is preserved in death.
‫أجل، لكنها محفوظة في الموت.
'Cause I once landed there. So it's fixed, yeah?
‫لأنني هبطت هناك من قبل. لذا إنها ثابتة.
Hold that down.
‫ثبّتي ذلك.
I see them, Melanie.
‫أراهما يا "ميلاني".
Every living thing contains dead cells.
‫يحتوي كلّ كائن حي على خلايا ميتة.
Skin, nails, enamel.
‫بشرة وأظافر ومينا الأسنان.
Sutekh can see through the dead.
‫يستطيع "سوتيخ" الرؤية عبر الموتى.
Melanie, closer.
‫اقتربي يا "ميلاني".
Closer.
‫اقتربي.
Bring them to Sutekh.
‫أحضريهما إلى "سوتيخ".
Find the mother's name!
‫اعثري على اسم الأم!
2046.
‫سنة 2046.
Thank you.
‫شكرًا.
I was in this building for the overthrow of Roger ap Gwilliam.
‫كنت في هذا المبنى ‫للإطاحة بـ"روجر آب غويليام".
It was the Department of Health.
‫كان مبنى وزارة الصحة.
It'll have the DNA.
‫لذا سيحتوي على الحمض النووي.
So, we're, like, hacking a computer?
‫هل سنخترق حاسوبًا؟
Sort of thing, yeah.
‫نوعًا ما، أجل.
Okay. The DNA list was locked away under top security.
‫حسنًا. وُضعت لائحة الحمض النووي ‫داخل نظام أمني مشدد.
But guess who invented the security.
‫لكن احزرا من اخترع النظام الأمني.
Come on. Come on. Come on. Come on.
‫هيا.
Yes! Yes.
‫أجل!
Okay. Mel, you better keep watch.
‫حسنًا. "ميل"، تابعي المراقبة.
Sutekh's servants could be anywhere.
‫قد يكون أتباع "سوتيخ" في أي مكان.
And don't take any risks.
‫لكن لا تخاطري.
We're all getting out of this.
‫سنخرج جميعًا من هذا الأمر أحياء.
Don't worry about me.
‫لا تقلق بشأني.
Find that name.
‫اعثر على ذلك الاسم.
Submit to me, Melanie.
‫أذعني لي يا "ميلاني".
That's me.
‫هذا اسمي.
So, what do we do now?
‫ماذا نفعل الآن؟
Press search.
‫نضغط زر البحث.
Somewhere in there is your mother's name.
‫اسم والدتك في مكان ما هنا.
- And maybe we can use it to fight Sutekh.
‫وربما بوسعنا استخدامه لمحاربة "سوتيخ".
Searching 76 million people.
‫يبحث بين 76 مليون شخص.
Who is she?
‫من هي؟
Melanie, Melanie, Melanie.
‫"ميلاني".
Here, I see you.
‫هنا، أراك.
Submit to the will of Sutekh.
‫أذعني لإرادة "سوتيخ".
Keep looking.
‫واصلي البحث.
Wha--
‫ماذا…
What does it mean?
‫ما معنى ذلك؟
- She died.
‫لقد ماتت.
Ruby, I'm sorry.
‫آسف يا "روبي".
I loved you, Mel.
‫أحببتك يا "ميل".
And what good did love do, Doctor?
‫وما نفع الحب يا دكتور؟
When did it ever help?
‫متى كان مفيدًا؟
Now give me the name.
‫أخبريني بالاسم الآن.
- But what does it mean? Give Sutekh the name.
‫- لكن ما معنى ذلك؟ ‫- أخبري "سوتيخ" بالاسم.
Bring me the Time Lord and the child and their precious secret.
‫أحضري إليّ سيد الزمن والفتاة وسرّهما الثمين.
I bring you a gift, holy Sutekh.
‫أحضرت لك هدية يا "سوتيخ" المقدّس.
Excellent.
‫ممتاز.
The last two creatures in existence to die at your hand.
‫آخر مخلوقين في الوجود ليموتا على يديك.
Then you can end our wretched half-life so that silence can reign.
‫ثم حينها بوسعك إنهاء حياتنا البائسة ‫ليسود الصمت.
And you can stand alone for all eternity,
‫ويمكنك أن تظل وحيدًا إلى الأبد
gazing upon your empire of dust and ice and oblivion.
‫لتحدّق إلى إمبراطوريتك ‫من الغبار والجليد والنسيان.
Show me the name.
‫أريني الاسم.
Show me, child.
‫أريني يا فتاة.
- Sutekh. - Bring the name to me.
‫- "سوتيخ". ‫- أحضري الاسم إليّ.
Sutekh, I promise you I will worship you if you just allow--
‫"سوتيخ"، أعدك بأنني سأعبدك إن سمحت…
Resist.
‫أنت تقاوم.
You have lived for far too long, little Lord of Time.
‫عشت أطول مما ينبغي يا سيد الزمن.
- I've got the name. - No! No!
‫- عرفت الاسم. ‫- لا!
I'll give it to you. Can you just let him go?
‫سأخبرك به إن سمحت له بالرحيل.
Don't. Don't.
‫لا تخبريه.
- The screen, it found the name.
‫عثرت الشاشة على الاسم.
- But I don't understand...
‫لكنني لا أفهم،
...and I wish I could.
‫وليتني أستطيع الفهم.
It's the only thing that I've ever wanted for all these years.
‫إنه الشيء الوحيد الذي أردته ‫طوال تلك السنوات.
But now I've found it.
‫لكنني الآن عثرت عليه.
And I don't understand.
‫ولا أفهم.
- But maybe you can.
‫لكن ربما بوسعك أن تفهم.
Maybe this is for you.
‫ربما هذا من أجلك.
Waited for so long.
‫انتظرت فترة طويلة جدًا.
You great big god of nothing.
‫يا إله العدم.
No!
‫لا!
'Cause I knew, Sutekh. I knew.
‫لأنني عرفت يا "سوتيخ".
She's too cold.
‫إنها أبرد من اللازم.
Listen to me.
‫اسمعيني.
This way.
‫من هنا.
Die at the hand of Sutekh.
‫موتا بيد "سوتيخ".
No!
‫لا!
I'm back.
‫لقد عدت.
- Into the vortex.
‫إلى الدوامة.
Got it.
‫أثبّتها.
You saw all of time and space with me, Sutekh.
‫رأيت كلّ الزمان والمكان معي يا "سوتيخ".
So I thought, "What if you see it again?"
‫لذا تساءلت، "ماذا إن رأيته مجددًا؟"
What happens if you bring death to death?
‫ماذا سيحدث إن جلبت الموت إلى الموت؟
You bring life!
‫تجلب الحياة!
Oh, that clever boy!
‫ذلك الشاب الذكي!
Bring death to death everywhere!
‫لنجلب الموت إلى الموت في كلّ مكان!
Hold that and that.
‫ثبّتي هذه وتلك.
What's happening?
‫ماذا يحدث؟
- Life, Ruby. Life.
‫الحياة يا "روبي".
We bring life to the whole flipping universe.
‫نجلب الحياة للكون بأكمله.
Okay. Vortis.
‫حسنًا. "فورتيس".
Tigella.
‫"تايغيلا".
Vox.
‫"فوكس".
Messaline. Calufrax.
‫"ميسالين". "كالوفراكس".
Spiridon.
‫"سبايريدون".
Telos.
‫"تيلوس".
Shan Shen.
‫"شان شين".
Welcome back, the Ood.
‫مرحبًا بعودة الأود.
And there, there.
‫وهناك.
The planet is called Agua Santina.
‫يُدعى هذا الكوكب "أغوا سانتينا".
With a spoon.
‫بملعقة.
We fought a monster.
‫حاربنا وحشًا.
And now...
‫والآن…
I must become a monster.
‫يجب أن أصير وحشًا.
Sutekh the Destroyer.
‫"سوتيخ" المدمر.
The lord god of death itself.
‫إله الموت ذاته.
You win.
‫أنت فزت.
Because I pride myself--
‫لأنني أفخر…
I pride myself that I am better than you.
‫لأنني أفخر بأنني أفضل منك.
- Because if you're death... - No!
‫- لأن إن كنت أنت الموت… ‫- لا!
...then I must represent life.
‫…فلا بد أنني أمثّل الحياة.
Surely that's what I am. Life.
‫هذا ما أنا عليه بالتأكيد. الحياة.
And that's how you win, Sutekh.
‫وهكذا تفوز يا "سوتيخ".
Because you turned me into this.
‫لأنك حوّلتني إلى هذا.
I am the one that brings death.
‫أنا من يجلب الموت.
No!
‫لا!
Sir.
‫سيدي.
But I'm still me.
‫لكنني ما زلت كما أنا.
I've still got my memories, my family. All of that's still true, is it?
‫ما زلت أحتفظ بذكرياتي عن عائلتي. ‫كلّ هذا حقيقي، صحيح؟
Absolutely.
‫بالتأكيد.
You are who you are.
‫أنت لن تتغيري.
The god of death created life.
‫شكّل إله الموت حياة.
And he gave you a very good brain.
‫ومنحك ذكاءً شديدًا.
Anything to help. I don't mind.
‫سأفعل أي شيء للمساعدة. لا أمانع.
I'll make the tea.
‫سأعدّ الشاي.
Did you make this tea?
‫هل أعددت هذا الشاي؟
I did, yes.
‫أجل.
- Don't make the tea. - Oh!
‫لا تعدّي الشاي.
Ooh, Christopher!
‫"كريستوفر"!
You should've seen me.
‫كان ينبغي أن تروني.
I had to walk home.
‫كان عليّ السير إلى المنزل.
I got in, and your gran was telling me off for not dusting.
‫حين دخلت، وبختني جدتك ‫لأنني لم أنظّف الغبار.
- Cherry.
‫"تشيري".
But I wanted to say--
‫لكنني أردت أن أقول…
Oh, don't, Mum. It's all right.
‫لا تفعلي يا أمي. لا بأس.
I wanted to say thank you, Doctor.
‫أردت أن أشكرك يا دكتور.
You brought her home.
‫أعدتها إلى ديارها.
You brought all of us back from, well, who-knows-where.
‫أعدتنا جميعًا من غياهب المجهول.
Do you remember what happened when you...
‫هل تتذكرين ما حدث حين…
- We've done it. DNA retrieval, 100%.
‫- فعلناها. ‫- استعادة الحمض النووي، 100 بالمئة.
Wow.
‫عجبًا.
My mother.
‫أمي.
Louise Alison Miller.
‫"لويز أليسون ميلر".
Thirty-five years old.
‫35 سنة.
Fifteen, when she gave birth to you.
‫كان عمرها 15 سنة حين أنجبتك.
Records say her stepfather was-- Well, he was trouble.
‫تقول السجلات إن زوج أمها كان مصدر متاعب.
I think she did the right thing getting you out of that house.
‫أظن أنها فعلت الصواب ‫بإخراجك من ذلك المنزل.
She must have hidden the pregnancy.
‫لا بد أنها أخفت الحمل.
Father, William Benjamin Garnet.
‫الأب "ويليام بنجامين غارنيت".
Fifteen at the time.
‫كان يبلغ 15 سنة حينها.
Louise moved to Coventry at the age of 18.
‫انتقلت "لويز" إلى "كوفنتري" في سن 18 سنة.
Did well. Got a degree.
‫أبلت حسنًا وحصلت على شهادة دراسية.
She's a nurse.
‫إنها ممرضة.
That's what I don't understand. She-- [chuckles] She's so ordinary.
‫هذا ما لا أفهمه. إنها عادية جدًا.
She's wonderful.
‫إنها مدهشة.
No, she's wonderful, and she's ordinary, but I love her for that.
‫لا، إنها مدهشة، وهي عادية، ‫وأُحبها لهذا السبب.
I just...
‫لكنني…
How did she stay invisible... ...from a god?
‫كيف أخفت نفسها عن إله؟
She defeated Sutekh.
‫هزمت "سوتيخ".
She was important...
‫كانت مهمة…
because we think she's important. It's how everything happens.
‫لأننا نظن أنها مهمة. هكذا يحدث كلّ شيء.
Every war, every religion, every love story.
‫كلّ حرب وكلّ عقيدة وكلّ قصة حُب.
We invest things with significance.
‫نغرس الأهمية في الأشياء.
So while the whole of creation was turning around her,
‫بينما كانت محور الخليقة كلها،
it made her sheer existence more powerful than Time Lords and gods.
‫جعل ذلك وجودها ذاته ‫أقوى من أسياد الزمن والآلهة.
In the end, the most important person in the universe was the most ordinary.
‫في نهاية المطاف، كان أهم شخص في الكون ‫أكثر شخص عادي.
A scared little girl making her baby safe.
‫فتاة مراهقة خائفة ‫تتأكد من أن ابنتها في أمان.
But she pointed.
‫لكنها أشارت.
She did.
‫أجل.
She pointed at you, Doctor.
‫أشارت إليك يا دكتور.
She wasn't pointing at me.
‫لم تشر إليّ.
'Cause we cleaned up the VHS. Behind me was that lamp post.
‫لأننا حسّنا شريط الفيديو. ‫كان ورائي عمود إنارة.
- So? - It was a signpost.
‫- ماذا في ذلك؟ ‫- كانت لافتة.
She was pointing at the name of the road.
‫كانت تشير إلى اسم الشارع.
She was naming you.
‫كانت تختار اسمك.
God. I always thought I was called Ruby because the social workers chose it
‫رباه. لطالما ظننت أنني دُعيت "روبي" ‫لأن موظفي الخدمة الاجتماعية اختاروه
or the paramedics or whatever. But, no, it was her.
‫أو المسعفين أو ما شابه. لكن هي من اختارته.
My own mother chose it.
‫اختارت أمي اسمي.
My name is Ruby.
‫اسمي "روبي".
She's happy.
‫إنها سعيدة.
She's got a flat. She's got a fella named Mike.
‫تمتلك شقة ومرتبطة بشخص يُدعى "مايك".
She goes to Spain in three weeks.
‫ستسافر إلى "إسبانيا" خلال ثلاثة أسابيع.
And the point is,
‫والمغزى هو
is that she has had over 7,000 days to come and find you,
‫أنه أُتيحت لها أكثر من 7,000 يوم ‫لتأتي وتبحث عنك،
and she never has.
‫لكنها لم تفعل ذلك قط.
But I found her.
‫لكنني عثرت عليها.
With a time machine.
‫بمساعدة آلة زمن.
Is that fair?
‫هل هذا منصف؟
Louise Miller made her choices and...
‫"لويز ميلر" اختارت بالفعل…
I think we should leave that alone.
‫وعلينا ألّا نتابع الأمر أكثر.
What can I get you? - Uh, oat cappuccino, please.
‫- ماذا أُحضر لك؟ ‫- كابتشينو بحليب الشوفان رجاءً.
- Ruby? - That's me.
‫- "روبي"؟ ‫- هذه أنا.
I was named after a road.
‫سُميت تيمنًا باسم شارع.
Ruby Road.
‫شارع "روبي".
You left me by a church, 19 years ago.
‫تركتني أمام كنيسة قبل 19 سنة.
You left me where I was safe.
‫تركتني حيث كنت آمنة.
- I'm so sorry. - No, don't.
‫- أنا آسفة جدًا. ‫- لا تتأسفي.
- My baby.
‫صغيرتي.
- Ooh, that's nice.
‫هذا جميل.
I always thought I should get in touch.
‫لطالما فكرت في التواصل معك.
Every Christmas I thought, "Right, this is the year."
‫فكرت في كلّ كريسماس، "صحيح، هذه هي السنة."
But every Christmas I thought, "What if she hates me?"
‫لكن في كلّ كريسماس فكرت، "ماذا إن كرهتني؟"
There is no hatred in this house, darling.
‫لا تُوجد كراهية في هذا البيت يا عزيزتي.
But what we have got is photos.
‫لكن لدينا صورًا.
Yeah? I've got about 500.
‫- حقًا؟ ‫- لديّ 500 صورة تقريبًا.
Mm-hmm. Proper photos.
‫صور حقيقية.
I've printed them off.
‫طبعتها.
You wait till you see her at ten years old,
‫انتظري حتى ترينها في سن 10 سنوات،
dressed up as David Bowie.
‫متنكرة بهيئة "ديفيد بوي".
We're just gonna have a catch-up and a pizza and...
‫سنتحدث ونتناول البيتزا و…
Mum set up a bed in Gran's room so Louise can stay the night.
‫ترتب أمي فراشًا في غرفة جدتي ‫لتقضي "لويز" الليلة معنا.
And then we can head off. You and me.
‫ثم بوسعنا أنا وأنت أن ننطلق.
Where to?
‫إلى أين؟
Wherever you want.
‫إلى أي مكان تريده.
- Ruby. - Come out and join.
‫- "روبي". ‫- اخرج وانضم إلينا.
I've told her so much about you. She knows everything.
‫أخبرتها بالكثير عنك. إنها تعرف كلّ شيء.
- And... Hold on. Sorry.
‫و… انتظر. آسفة.
Leave that.
‫لنتجاهل ذلك.
And, no, I said, "Life with the Doctor is just mad."
‫وقلت، "الحياة مع الدكتور جنونية."
Hang on. I better...
‫انتظر. يجدر بي…
Oh, my God.
‫يا إلهي.
They think they've found him. My dad. William.
‫يظنون أنهم عثروا على أبي. "ويليام".
They think--
‫يظنون…
Because it turns out, his mum and dad still live at the same address,
‫لأنه تبيّن أن أباه وأمه ‫ما زالا يعيشان في العنوان نفسه،
but she never told him.
‫لكنها لم تخبره قط.
My mum, my real mum.
‫أقصد أمي الحقيقية.
So... [sighs] ...she never told Will about me, so he doesn't even know I exist.
‫لم تخبر "ويل" قط بشأني، ‫لا يعرف أنني موجودة حتى.
So we've gotta go and...
‫لذا عليّ الذهاب و…
I'm sorry.
‫أنا آسفة.
Don't be sorry.
‫لا تتأسفي.
Don't be sorry at all.
‫لا تتأسفي على الإطلاق.
Your life is out there now.
‫حياتك هناك في الخارج الآن.
I've shown you monsters and planets and legends.
‫أريتك وحوشًا وكواكب وأساطير.
But this...
‫لكن هذا…
But you could come and see my dad.
‫لكن بوسعك أن تأتي وتقابل أبي.
You don't do that, do you?
‫لا تفعل هذا، أليس كذلك؟
Will I ever see you again?
‫هل سأراك مجددًا؟
Of course you will.
‫بالطبع سترينني.
Your own granddaughter, you left her and never went back.
‫تركت حفيدتك ولم تعد إليها قط.
And that was my mistake.
‫وكانت تلك غلطتي.
Maybe I'll find her again one day.
‫ربما سأعثر عليها ثانيةً ذات يوم.
But you, Ruby Sunday, I will see again because you changed me.
‫لكنني سأراك ثانيةً يا "روبي صنداي" ‫لأنك غيّرتني.
I talk about family in a way that I never did before.
‫أتحدّث عن العائلة ‫بطريقة لم أتحدّث بها من قبل.
It's because of you.
‫وهذا بفضلك.
You have made my life bigger and better.
‫جعلت حياتي أثرى وأفضل.
And now, Ruby Sunday...
‫والآن يا "روبي صنداي"…
goodbye.
‫وداعًا.
I love you.
‫أُحبك.
Oh, she's so gorgeous.
‫إنها جميلة جدًا.
What made you walk away? Mum!
‫- ما الذي جعلك ترحلين؟ ‫- أمي!
...of the church on Ruby Road comes to an end.
‫قصة الكنيسة في شارع "روبي".
With a very happy ending for little Ruby Sunday.
‫بنهاية سعيدة جدًا لـ"روبي صنداي" الصغيرة.
But life goes on, doesn't it?
‫لكن الحياة تمضي، أليس كذلك؟
Ruthlessly.
‫من دون شفقة.
And what happens, you might wonder,
‫وقد تتساءلون، ماذا سيحدث…
oh, what happens to that mysterious traveller
‫أجل، ماذا سيحدث لهذا المسافر الغامض
in time and space known as the Doctor?
‫في الزمان والمكان الذي يُدعى الدكتور؟
I'm sorry to say, his story ends in absolute terror.
‫يؤسفني القول إن قصته ستنتهي برعب مطلق.
Night night.
‫طابت ليلتكم.